A Guide to the Papers of Emily Dickinson, ca. 1860-1955
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Emily Dickinson ca. 1860-1955
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7658, -a
This collection consists of ca. 45 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
7658 was deposited on August 20, 1964; 7658-a was deposited on April 4, 1990. Both were made gifts on July 1, 1991.
Biographical/Historical Information
Emily Dickinson (1830-1886) was an American lyrical poet, and an obsessively private writer; only seven of her some 1800 poems were published during her lifetime. Dickinson withdrew from social contact at the age of 23 and devoted herself in secret into writing.
Dickinson was born in Amherst, Massachusetts, to a family well known for educational and political activity. Her father, an orthodox Calvinist, was a lawyer and treasurer of Amherst College, and also served in Congress. She was educated at Amherst Academy (1834-1847) and Mount Holyoke Female Seminary (1847-1848). Around 1850 Dickinson started to write poems, first in fairly conventional style, but after ten years of practice she began to give room for experiments. From about 1858 she assembled many of her poems in packets of "fascicles," which she bound herself with needle and thread.
After the Civil War Dickinson restricted her contacts outside Amherst to exchange of letters, dressed only in white and saw few of the visitors who came to meet her. In fact, she spent most of her time in her room. Although she lived a secluded life, her letters reveal knowledge of the writings of John Keats, John Ruskin, and Sir Thomas Browne. Dickinson's emotional life remains mysterious, despite much speculation about a possible disappointed love affair. Two candidates have been presented: Reverend Charles Wadsworth, with whom she corresponded, and Samuel Bowles, editor of the Springfield Republican, to whom she addressed many poems.
After Dickinson's death in 1886, her sister Lavinia brought out her poems. She co-edited three volumes from 1891 to 1896. Despite its editorial imperfections, the first volume became popular. In the early decades of the twentieth century, Martha Dickinson Bianchi, the poet's niece, transcribed and published more poems, and in 1945 Bolts Of Melody essentially completed the task of bringing Dickinson's poems to the public. The publication of Thomas H. Johnson's 1955 edition of Emily Dickinson's poems finally gave readers a complete and accurate text.
Dickinson's works have had considerable influence on modern poetry. Her frequent use of dashes, sporadic capitalization of nouns, off-rhymes, broken meter, and unconventional metaphors have contributed her reputation as one of the most innovative poets of 19th-century American literature. Later feminist critics have challenged the popular conception of the poet as a reclusive, eccentric figure, and underlined her intellectual and artistic sophistication.
Scope and Content
The Papers of Emily Dickinson consist primarily of correspondence by Emily Dickinson and Lavinia Dickinson. Of interest are descriptions of the death of Thomas Gilbert Dickinson in 1883. The Miscellaneous Documents series contains some 30 negative photostats of forgeries of Emily Dickinson poems; the forgeries were created by an unidentified young man who claimed he was part of the Dickinson family. With the photostats is a lengthy description by Joan St. C. Crane concerning the discovery of the forgeries. Also within Miscellaneous Documents is the galley proof for the 1951 edition of Emily Dickinson by Richard Chase and brief biographical sketches of Emily Dickinson, Lavinia Dickinson, and Forrest Fayette Emerson by a member of the Emerson family.
Arrangement
The Papers of Emily Dickinson are arranged in three series. Series I: Literary Manuscripts, consists of one autograph poem by Emily Dickinson; Series II: Correspondence is divided into two subseries: Subseries A: letters of Emily Dickinson and Subseries B: letters of Lavinia Dickinson. Both subseries are arranged chronologically. Finally is Series III: Miscellaneous Documents.
Contents List
- Series I: Literary Manuscripts
  - "Just lost when I was saved!," [ca. 1860], AMs, 2 pp. on 1 l., #7658. (Folder 1)
    Identical to Dickinson's "Called back" as it was published in The Independent in March, 1891 prior to its appearance in Poems: Second Series in November, 1891.
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Subseries A: Emily Dickinson
    - E[mily] Dickinson to Mr. [Franklin Benjamin] Sanborn, [ca. 1873], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l., #7658. (Folder 2)
      Dickinson thanks Sanborn for some books by Shakespeare, which are "better than heaven for that is unavoidable while one may miss these." With TLS, Thomas Johnson to Waller [Barrett], 1955 October 12, regarding origin and provenance of this particular Dickinson letter.
    - E[mily] Dickinson to "Dear Clergyman" [Forrest Fayette Emerson], [ca.1885 September], 4 pp. on 2 l., #7658. (Folder 3)
      Discusses the death of "Little Gilbert." Mentions that Vinnie [Lavinia] "hoped too to speak with you of Helen of Colorado." Writes of Keats. Finally, in a postscript, reveals that she has no picture of "Little Gilbert." With handwritten transcription.
    - Emily [Dickinson] to [Eugenia], [ca. 1885 October 20], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope, #7658. (Folder 4)
      A short note to [Eugenia] asking her to "accept a smile which will last a life, if ripened in the sun?"
    - Emily [Dickinson] to "little cousin," [ca. 1885], ANS, 1 p. on 1 l., #7658. (Folder 5)
      Thanks her cousin for the flowers "which without lips have language."
    - Emily [Dickinson] to "Dear Friend" [Forrest Fayette Emerson], [ca. 1885-1886], ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l., #7658. (Folder 6)
      Offers thanks for the package with "its sacred contents." Hopes he is enjoying the climate with Mrs. Emerson.
    - E[mily] Dickinson to "Dear Friend," n.d., ANS, 1 p. on 1 l., #7658. (Folder 7)
      A short note: "We recollect you, which if a frugal phrase, has sumptuous meanings."
  - Subseries B: Lavinia Dickinson
    - [Lavinia Dickinson] to "My Dear Friends" [Forrest Fayette Emerson and Harriet Andrews Hartwell Emerson?], [1883] November 16, AL fragment, 4 pp. on 1 l., #7658. (Folder 8)
      Emily and Lavinia have been spending all their time trying to console Austin since the death of Austin's son, [Thomas] Gilbert Dickinson, on October 5, 1883. Emily was alarmingly ill after Gilbert's death, and is "still very delicate."
    - "Vinnie" [Lavinia Dickinson] to "My dear Friends" [Forrest Fayette Emerson and Harriet Andrews Hartwell Emerson?], [post 1883] August 31, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l., #7658. (Folder 9)
      Thanks them for invitation to visit; is sorry to have missed Emerson when he was in Amherst; comments that Newport is delightful, and mentions that Austin Dickinson may visit them soon.
    - Vinnie [Lavinia] Dickinson to "My Dear Friends" [Forrest Fayette Emerson and Harriet Andrews Hartwell Emerson?], [1884] January 24, ALS, 6 pp. on 2 l., #7658. (Folder 10)
      Austin comforted by his letter, and is "brave and patient." Discusses the "mystery of Gilbert's death." Emily remains "frail" since Gilbert's death.
    - Lavinia [Dickinson] to "My Dear Friend," [ca. 1887] September 16, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l., #7658. (Folder 11)
      Discusses the weather and hopes for a visit from the correspondent.
    - Lavinia Dickinson to [Caroline Healey] Dall, 1895 January 29, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l., #7658. (Folder 12)
      Lavinia corrects false statements about her family. "Emily never had any love disaster," Emily found "the life with her books at nature so congenial" that she continued "to live it," and that their father "was the grandest of men." Lavinia is "determined to extinguish all untruth relating" to Emily.
- Series III: Miscellaneous Documents
  - Brief biographical sketches of Emily Dickinson, Lavinia Dickinson, and Forrest Fayette Emerson, n.d., TMs, 3 pp. on 2 l., #7658. (Folder 13)
    Presumably written by a niece or nephew of the Emerson's.
  - Negative photostats of forgeries of Emily Dickinson poems, n.d., 30 items, #7658. (Folder 14)
    Includes a typed description, by Joan St. C. Crane, about the origins of the forgeries.
  - Photostats of forgeries of Emily Dickinson letters, [ca. 1959-1969], 9 items, #7658. (Folder 15)
  - Emily Dickinson by Richard Chase, proof sheets, 1951, 1 volume, #7658-a.
    Advance galley proof from William Sloan Associates, Inc., New York, New York, 217 pp.